שבוע טוב. Shavua tov. All right, today's דף daf is what דף
daf is it?
קנ"ח? Kuf-Nun-Chet?
קמ"ח. Kuf-Mem-Chet. All right, I don't even know where I am. קמ"ח.
Kuf-Mem-Chet. 148. Now, I have another פרק perek right. Okay.
There it is. All right,
so yesterday, I just want to spend a minute to talk about
some of the הלכות halakhot that came up yesterday. We were talking
about bathing in, we were talking about concerns about squeezing towels where
basically we said that we're not concerned if a normal person dries
himself off with a towel even one person that he'll come to
squeeze it. But we did also mention the איסור issur about showering
in hot water. And it quoted the, and it said that our
משנה mishna was רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who said actually there's not
a problem to shower in hot water. Actually, I think I misspoke
yesterday, while that's the position, that's actually the case by יום טוב,
Yom Tov, at least that's the way I פוסקן pasken by יום
טוב. Yom Tov.
By שבת, Shabbos, based on the earlier גמרא Gemara that discussed this
איסור issur about bathing in hot water at length, even water that
was preheated, the conclusion is and it's the way it's פוסקן paskened
in שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and the רמב"ם Rambam and all the
and pretty much everywhere, is that even a shower in hot water,
your whole body in hot water, even via shower is not allowed
because of a concern of the Jews going to bathhouses and the
heating up the water on שבת. Shabbat.
So what we are allowed to do on שבת Shabbos is individual
limbs or cold water on the whole body in terms of a
shower. Bath, אשכנזים Ashkenazim in general don't immerse the whole body even
in cold water with the exception of מקוה. Mikvah. So on שבת
Shabbat if it's not a case of like somebody who's sick where
the rule is different, the ruling is that you can either do
individual limbs in preheated hot water or you know depending on whether
without questions about using hot water in apartment buildings on שבת Shabbos
which I'm not going to get into, but individual limbs is not
under that גזירה gezeira or the whole body in cold water. An
interesting question is what about the whole body again by that I
mean a shower not a bath, what about a shower in lukewarm
water, warm water? Is it that you can't use the hot water
or you can't, you know, you can't, the bathing can't be with,
you know, can't be a hot bath, can't be hot water? It
sounds more because obviously when you make lukewarm water it's a mixture
of the two if on you know if so you're using the
hot water on שבת Shabbat you're just mixing it with cold water.
So it seems more that it's the
latter, which means that again unless it's a special really a special
circumstance, even a warm shower is a problem on שבת Shabbat which
is of course what everybody practices. And all of that is related
to this concern about bathhouses and heating it up. On יום טוב
Yom Tov the issue is different and we're not going to discuss
that at length, but on יום טוב Yom Tov it has a
lot more to do with you know what's considered צורך כל הגוף
tzorach kol haguf and since most people, you know at least in
America bathe on a daily basis with hot water, there are a
lot of פוסקים poskim myself included that feel that you can take
a hot shower on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Again when you do
those you have to be careful about squeezing out the towel, squeezing
out your hair and all those things. Okay. So that's just in
terms of the shower and hot water. The גמרא Gemara says our
משנה mishna implies that it's okay but even on שבת Shabbos but
in practice we rule that it's not okay but individual limbs or
cold water's a different story.
What about swimming on שבת? Shabbos?
Swimming as I said for אשכנזים Ashkenazim full immersion even in cold
water is a מנהג אשכנזים minhag Ashkenazim going back a you know
good 800 years or so that we don't do full immersion in
cold water because of these incidental or tangential concerns of squeezing hair,
squeezing towel, etc. ספרדים Sefardim actually do, ספרדים Sefardim do swim, go
swim on שבת. Shabbos.
If you don't squeeze out anything.
No, no, no, but the מנהג minhag is obviously the מנהג minhag
is not to do it at all because of a concern it
might come to that. That's the אשכנזי Ashkenazi מנהג. minhag. Again when
there are health concerns it's different. But for ספרדים Sefardim they actually
so אשכנזים Ashkenazim don't fully immerse themselves meaning in a bath or
in a swimming pool even in cold water on שבת Shabbos again
with the exception of מקוה, Mikvah, ספרדים Sefardim do. So that's that.
Moving on one last point though about the other thing we mentioned
yesterday about the dirt on the clothes.
So here although the גמרא Gemara had all of these qualifications about
only black and only you know new and black and all these
things, you will remember that we a while ago spoke about a
problem about like rubbing your garment from dirt you know rubbing from
the inside, rubbing from the outside, you basically remember that? So basically
so how does that work and that seems to be regardless of
the garment. So how do you sort of reconcile those two? Is
it like only black and only whatever? So one way to reconcile
it is that if it's real dirt, something that really stains or
whatever, then it's a problem regardless of the garment. If it however
is something like dust, dust really only is seen as a real
staining on like a new black garment
you know. Another approach, however, is that it's a difference about how
you're getting it off. That if they're, you know, vigorously rubbing it,
that's a problem regardless. If you're just like, you know, wiping it
off, maybe that's a special problem like by dust. In general, the
general ruling is though, that it's not so much really the color
of the garment or how new it is or any of those
issues. The general ruling is that to get something off from the
surface is okay, to rub it out if it's embedded and it's
a stain, you know, that's problematic. So that's generally the guide. Crusted...
Yeah, if it's crusted on, so you can sort of scrape it
off as long as you're just scraping off the surface, but once
it's not just getting the surface stuff off, but it's actually a
stain and you're getting a stain out, then exactly what the line
is is not always 100% clear, but then that's a problem. But
to scrape something off from the surface, you know, that's okay as
long as you're not getting it out from embedded within within the
garment.
But you can't use water regardless, right?
Yeah, water is a separate issue. Okay, anyway, that was just a
quick, you know, somewhat halachic conclusion of the other day. Anything more
about the towels? No. Let's get to the bottom of the גמרא
Gemara now. The אין מחזירין את השבר. Ein machzirin et hashever. So
you cannot restore a dislocated... you cannot restore a like a broken
bone, okay, which is like wild, you know, because we would say
that that's my god, that's like a serious סכנת אבר sakanat eiver
or something. So אמר רבי חננא, Amar Rabbi Chanana, so let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says to this. Says רבי חננא בר
טלטיא Rabbi Chanana bar Taltiya of בגדד Bagdad maybe, אמר שמואל ומשמואל
הלכה והלכה היא מחזירין את השבר.
Amar Shmuel umishmuel halacha
v'halacha hi machzirin et hashever. You can restore a broken bone. רבה
בר בר חנה איקלע לפומבדיתא. Rabbah bar bar Chana ikla l'Pumbedita. So
רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana came to פומבדיתא. Pumbedita.
לא על לפרקי דרב יהודה. Lo al l'pirkei d'Rav Yehuda. He didn't
go to the to the שיעור shiur
of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. שדריה לאדא דיילא. Shadrei l'Ada Dayala. So
so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda sent this office, you know, like some
attendant. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, אדא דיילא, Ada Dayala, the
second line, רש"י Rashi says מנסטראל. menestrel. So so some type of
anyway of of assistant. דיילא... Dayala... I'm sorry, לאדא דיילא. l'Ada Dayala.
אמר
ליה זיל גרביה. Amar lei zil garbei. Go and basically grab him
by his clo... you know, grab him, drag him in, force his
clothes, force him to come. אזל גרביה. Azal garbei. He went. אתא.
Ata. So fine, so רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana
didn't have much choice. This guy was like you know taking away
his his clothes or what you know whatever, שלעפינג shlepping him along.
So אשכחיה, Ashkachei, so he found that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda דקדרש,
d'ka-darash, that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was saying אין מחזירין את השבר,
Ein machzirin et hashever, like our משנה Mishnah says, you cannot restore
the bone on שבת, Shabbat, you know, if there's a break. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, הכי אמר רב חננא בר טלטיא אמר שמואל הלכה
מחזירין את השבר. hachi amar Rav Chanana bar Taltiya amar Shmuel halacha
machzirin et hashever. One minute, ורב חננא בר טלטיא v'Rav Chanana bar
Taltiya says in the name of שמואל Shmuel הלכה מחזירין את השבר.
halacha machzirin et hashever. We don't rule like our משנה. Mishnah. We
rule you can put it back, which is pretty fascinating, you know,
not quoting an opposing ברייתא Baraita or משנה, Mishnah, another תנאי Tannai
source, just saying that שמואל Shmuel disagrees. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so
he says, wow, he says that's that's really good to know. חנא
דידן, Chana didan, חנא, Chana, this חנא בר טלטיא Chana bar Taltiya
was from here, from פומבדיתא. Pumbedita. ושמואל דידן, u'Shmuel didan, and שמואל
Shmuel is one of us. So both שמואל Shmuel and this person
who is saying in his name were from פומבדיתא. Pumbedita. ולא שמיע
לי, v'lo shmia li, and I never heard this teaching. So it's
now you could say I never heard it and therefore I don't
believe it, but presumably you know because these guys were from from
around here, but that's not what he's saying. He's saying it's so
good that you came, because here these were even members of our
own community and I never heard this teaching. So ולאו בדינא גבייתך,
v'lav b'dina gavitach, didn't wasn't it justified that I sort of you
know forced you to come because now we learned something that now
you've enlightened all of us? So you know, what? No. No, I
mean he's saying you know he's being he's being
rhetorical, but he's not being sarcastic. He's saying didn't I do it
what wasn't I justified in doing it? Because I mean that's at
least the way רש"י Rashi reads it. You know you could you
could read the גמרא Gemara the exact opposite. You could read the
גמרא Gemara like I don't believe anything you're saying and I shouldn't
have dragged you here. But no, it doesn't sound like that. It
sounds like he's saying look, it's good that I שלעפט shlepped you
here.
Still סברא sevara though, right?
Let's take a look. We're not done. Okay, מי שנפרקה ידו. Mi
shenifreka yado. Now it goes in and says if you have a
dislocated arm or shoulder, you can put cold water on it, but
you cannot... and if it... but you can't directly put cold water,
it's a healing process, but you can bathe it and if it
gets better it gets better. So the גמרא Gemara says רב אוויא
הוה יתיב קמיה דרב יוסף. Rav Avya hava yativ kamei d'Rav Yosef.
רב אוויא Rav Avya was sitting in front of רב יוסף. Rav
Yosef. שנייה ליה ידיה. Shanya lei yadei. His hand like he so
he like did something unusual with his arm, his hand. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, הכי מאי? hachi mai? Like the other גמרא Gemara about
folding the garment. What what if your what if your hand is
dislocated like this? You know, what can I do then? So he
says so הכי אסור, hachi assur, he says it's forbidden. והכי מאי?
v'hachi mai? How about like this? What about that? So אמר ליה
אסור. Amar lei assur. Okay, it's אסור. assur. אדהכי אישפח ידיה. Adahachi
ishpach yadei. So while he was doing it, of course he you
know he injured his hand in the result of doing this whole
thing. אמר ליה, Amar lei, מאי דיבעיא לך? mai dibaiya lach?
So he said look I don't get it. What was your question?
תנן, tenan, the משנה Mishnah says, מי שנפרקה ידו או רגלו לא
יצפם בצונן אבל רוחץ כדרכו. Mi shenifreka yado o raglo lo yetzapem
b'tzonen aval rochetz k'darko. נתרפא נתרפא. nitrape nitrape.
It says don't do it in cold water, but you can like
just bathe it normally. So why were you asking all these questions
about what it this, what it that? So אמר ליה, Amar lei,
because ולא תנן V'lo tnan אין מחזירין את השבר ein machzirin et
hashever because,
well the משנה Mishnah also says you don't put back a, you
don't restore a broken bone. ואמר רב חנא בר תניא אמר שמואל
V'amar Rav Chana bar Tanyah amar Shmuel and we just got through
saying הלכה מחזירין את השבר halacha machzirin et hashever you do put
back a broken bone. So I figured if you can put back
a broken bone, maybe if you have a serious dislocated shoulder, maybe
you could also do you know restore that, you know, it should
be the same idea. Dislocated but not broken. So right. So אמר
ליה, Amar lei, what he said back to him, כולהו בחדא מחתא
מחתינהו kulehu bechada machta machtinhu what do you think? You think they're
all taught in one bundle? They're all the same thing? היכא דאתמר
אתמר והיכא דלא אתמר לא אתמר. Heicha d'itmar itmar v'heicha d'lo itmar
lo itmar. Where it was said it was said, where it wasn't
said it wasn't said. So just because we rule against our משנה
Mishnah by the broken bone, doesn't mean that we rule against it
in the all other places. So the הלכה halacha about the dislocation
is a very strict construction.
Yes, it is.
Look, and the reality is that again it's very hard for us
to understand this. I mean, obviously you'd understand why a broken bone
is more serious, but it's hard for us to understand any of
this because the general הלכה halacha as we have, as we פוסקן,
pasken, it's not necessarily clear this way from the גמרא, Gemara, but
that even if it's a חולה שאין בו סכנה, choleh she'ein bo
sakanah, you're allowed to do, you don't have to worry about these
concerns of רפואה. refuah. Not only do you not have to worry
about the concerns of רפואה, refuah, you can even violate rabbinic, other
rabbinic restrictions. There's a question about how directly can you violate rabbinic
restrictions, אמירה לעכו"ם, amirah l'akum, even a ישראל Yisrael and so on,
but there's a lot of allowances for חולה שאין בו סכנה choleh
she'ein bo sakanah and it would certainly seem to any of us
that somebody with a broken bone or a dislocated shoulder is in,
you know, is in the category of חולה כל הגוף. choleh kol
haguf. It's not what we call מיחוש בעלמא, michush b'alma, a little
discomfort. So it's quite strange that the גמרא Gemara here is, the
משנה Mishnah is very strict and the גמרא Gemara at least you
see an initial move, at least in the most extreme cases, and
in practice of course we're, you know, we're pretty lenient on all
cases that are in this type of category. How we got from
the גמרא's Gemara strictness to our leniency I'd have to take a
look
at how, you know, how
it explains, you know, this גמרא, Gemara, the jump from this גמרא
Gemara to actual practice. Anyway, הדרן עלך חבית. Hadran alach chavit. So
that is the end of חבית Chavit which again a lot of
this was about food related issues, some דאורייתא, de'oraita, some דרבנן. derabanan.
We ended by things about around squeezing, squeezing food, squeezing a towel,
bathing and clothing, all these other, you know, and then back to
רפואה, refuah, all these other related issues. And again just to repeat
what I said at the beginning in terms of the bathing issue,
you know, on שבת Shabbos because of the concern of bathhouses, hot
water is, אשכנזים Ashkenazim number one have a מנהג minhag not to
immerse even in cold water, you know, swimming, bathtubs, whatever. And in
terms of hot water that's a problem if it's the whole body
even as a shower. So that's that for at least on שבת.
Shabbos.
And in terms of, you know, the last thing we also we
said about clothes again, it's the degree something is embedded within the
clothes, any, you know, any rubbing or scraping or whatever getting it
out, you know, is problematic. Some of the limitations of the גמרא
Gemara about black and new and whatever are more for, you know,
more trivial things like, like some type of a dust or, or
that nature. Also I did also want to add again that when
we discussed how does it be, how what does it mean in
the גמרא Gemara that you're, you want to get it off and
then the גמרא Gemara is saying you're not, you're not מקפיד makpid
on it. So I think I said yesterday but I just wanted
to confirm that the way we, that we define the word מקפיד
makpid in that previous גמרא Gemara halachically, as like I said, is
that, you know, it's so bad you wouldn't wear it, you know,
it's so bad you wouldn't wear it unless you got it out.
But again those severe limitations are more about when you're not as
vigorously getting it out or when it's more something trivial as dust.
In general if you're really working to get something out of being
embedded that's a problem regardless. Yes.
So you know, just something very practical. Let's say you have this
spill, you know you take these paper towels, they get soaking wet.
I mean I'm not supposed to move it because it's going to,
you'll squeeze some...
No, so again, again, I'm not going to give the full answer
but I will say we also had the statement about if you're,
have your clothes are soaking wet you can walk with them. There's
one thing about a concern of squeezing, there's another thing about it
just normally, naturally sort of like dripping. And also, you know, but
there are times where it depends somewhat on the parameters. If you're
picking it up... I understand, but that might be just be just,
yeah but you're not squeezing it out, it's just anyway, I'm not
going to give, there are times it depends, and I'm not going
to go into the details. Okay, let's take a look at the
next פרק. perek. שואל אדם מחבירו, Sho'el adam m'chaveiro, now we move
on to a totally different issue. So if that issue was more
around like household things and דרבנן's derabanan about that, about food, a
lot around food, this פרק perek begins with the, with issues about
concerns around business types of activities. They might be in the kitchen
but the concern is less like you'll come to do a דאורייתא,
de'oraita, you'll come to squeeze it out, or the type of עובדין
דחול, uvdin d'chol, you know, but it, it's more things that could
be associated with the world of like מקח וממכר mekach umimkar of
transactions and business. Let's take a look. שואל אדם מחבירו כדי יין
וכדי שמן. Sho'el adam m'chaveiro kadei yayin v'kadei shemen. You can borrow
from your friend on שבת, Shabbos, like pitchers
you know of wine or of oil, ובלבד שלא יאמר לו u'bilvad
shelo yomar lo
don't say to him הלויני, halveini, lend me. get to me. Okay.
Now וכן, v'chein, right, וכן אשה מחברתה ככרות, v'chein ishah michaveirta kikaros,
a woman can borrow from her friend loaves of bread. ואם אינו
מאמינו, v'im eino ma'amino, now let's say the guy is afraid that,
yeah, you know, I'm going to give you a whole barrel of
wine because you got guests, I want to get paid, and but,
you know, we don't have any record of it, you're not paying
me on שבת, Shabbos, I don't, I'm maybe I'm not totally trusting
that you'll
your honesty, or maybe I'm just afraid you'll forget or whatever. So
what do I do? מניח טליתו אצלו ועושה עמו חשבון לאחר שבת.
maniach taliso etzlo v'oseh imo cheshbon l'achar Shabbos. So you can leave
by me, again you're not paying me, you'll leave your coat with
me, you'll leave your watch with me, you know, and then you
will and then we'll work it out after שבת. Shabbos.
So that's not like a פקדון? pikadon?
Yeah I know. So the funny thing is that under other circumstances
you would say that that's collateral. But that's if you explicitly said
like, okay, you owe me a hundred dollars, here's this, this is
collateral. Here you're basically just, you know, just saying like, I'll pick
up my watch after שבת. Shabbos. So again by the way you're
framing it, you leave your
watch by me?
Yeah, that's a good question. Can I say, well, before I lend
you my barrel, you know, could you, no but can't say you
lend, before I let you, so let, we don't, why don't you
leave your watch here and then like, that's a good question, at
what stage does that become essentially indicating that it's transactional and a
פקדון? pikadon?
Yeah, but that's in a different too, though. This isn't about business,
but about the, that the guy will have to write down in
the, well
that might be what the business concerns are, and then
the, the
פקדון pikadon has something to do, like if I leave my watch
with you, then I don't have to write it down, cause I
have your watch.
Mmm, that's a good point. Okay, so we, so as I was
going to, so, so if you're right, if the concern of business
types of transactional activities is not just, is not just that it's
inherently problematic, but that you'll come to write it down, which is
actually what the גמרא Gemara is about to say, so you're saying
what about certain types of activities? Yeah, but you know if that
were true, well we'll have to get to it, but you, it's
a good point that you could do, the whole point of a
פקדון pikadon is that it obviates the need of making a record.
So even if it was more explicitly businesslike. You know, of course
a sale, also you don't have to write down, you're actually paying
for it and taking it. So, but that's a good point and
the גמרא Gemara does emphasize that the concern here is the writing
concern. Okay, but let me just finish the משנה. Mishnah. וכן ערב
פסח בירושלים שחל להיות בשבת. v'chein Erev Pesach biYerushalayim shechal lihyos b'Shabbos.
How about if, if שבת Shabbos is ערב פסח Erev Pesach and
you didn't buy your animal before שבת? Shabbos? מניח טליתו אצלו. maniach
taliso etzlo. You leave your טלית tallis by the guy who's, who
has the sheep. ונוטל את פסחו v'notel es pischo and you take
your, and you take your lamb. ועושה עמו חשבון לאחר יום טוב
v'oseh imo cheshbon l'achar Yom Tov and after יום טוב Yom Tov
you, you work it all out. Now, I guess a question in
a second, but I did want to say also, what's the difference
between saying שואל, shoel, you say I want to be שואל, shoel,
versus I want to be לוה. loveh. So רש"י Rashi says that
שואל shoel suggests for a brief period of time and I'm going
to pay you back like, you know, tomorrow or something, whereas לוה
loveh suggests for a long period of time and there's a greater
concern you'll come to forget and therefore there's a concern that that
will make you more want to write it down. תוספות Tosfos says,
which I think is more, you know, intuitive, is that, and we
don't have, I don't think we have this difference in English, that
שואל shoel means lending a object that you're going to give back
the object itself, like I want to borrow your car. Whereas opposed
to לוה loveh means I want to borrow a hundred dollars, I'm
going to spend the hundred dollars, and I'll give you back a
different hundred dollars. That's לוה. loveh. לוה loveh is much often about
money and things that are used, but primarily about money. שואל shoel
is about like a durable object that you borrow it and you
give it back. We don't have a different word in English for
the two, do we? I don't think so. Anyway, so תוספות Tosfos
says, therefore, even though the reality of this case is, could, you
know, when you go to your neighbor and you say could I
borrow, could I borrow two eggs, right? First of all, half the
time you don't even mean can I borrow. You're gonna, you're not
gonna give it back. Okay, can I have? But it's nicer to
say can I borrow. But anyway, but even when you say can
I borrow, you know, what it does mean is you'll pay back
two eggs, but they're not going to be the same two eggs,
the same way I pay back a hundred dollars, it's not the
same hundred dollars. So תוספות Tosfos says yes, it's true, technically this
is more like הלואה halva'ah in the sense that you don't give
back the same thing. But when you use the language of שואל,
shoel, especially when it also is, you're taking an object and giving
an object, then it much more suggests that idea of something that
doesn't need to be written because it's like giving the same thing
back. Things that get spent, you know, there's a need to make
a record of it. Whereas things that are basically taken, used, and
given back, there's much less of a need of making a record.
So when I'm lending you my book, there's much less of a
need of making a record. So when you use that language, although
not technically true here, because you have to give you other eggs,
it much more suggests a different type of a transaction. You know,
you use it for a little bit of a time, you give
it back. It's not something I have to worry about and something
that I have to write down. So that's how תוספות Tosfos explains
the difference which really does make the most sense here.
Yeah, eggs, they get a wine, or right,
they're all food, right, they're
things that get used, you're not gonna like eat the bread, exactly.
So תוספות Tosfos says technically it is more of a הלואה, halva'ah,
but again when we frame it as שאילה, she'eilah, then that, you
know, makes it more clear that it's like not in that normal
realm of writing things down and of lending things for a long
period of time.
The משנה Mishnah: *Mishnah* sort of assumes, it
assumes
that we're talking about men, and it has to explicitly identify. אדם
*Adam*. I understand. You're coming from your vantage point that you want
things turned into neutral language and so on, but the משנה mishna
*Mishnah* is men writing laws about men and thinking about men as
the primary actors. So when it's talking about a woman, they have
to explicitly identify. And I think that they were just trying to
describe some common scenarios. So common scenarios. Right.
You're saying when the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* says you can do something,
if you want to include women, you have to add an additional...
I think in general...
No, no, no.
I didn't mean like legally it's assumed that women are excluded. But
I just meant that when the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* is describing, no,
I didn't mean as from a legal הלכתית *halachic* point of view.
I meant when the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* is describing a
scenario, so-and-so can borrow whatever, in the picture inside of the rabbi's
mind is a man, not a woman. So if they want to
describe a scenario that involves a woman, they would explicitly label it.
And women could do it, even though they're dealing with...
Even though the law would be the same. Right. But if they're
trying to say, so
it goes back to this question, though.
What does it add? Right. It still doesn't say why do you
have to יין *yayin* and שמן *shemen*, just say יין *yayin*. I
think sometimes the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* although the גמרא gemara *Gemara* sometimes
reads the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* with the same sort of exactitude as
it reads a biblical פסוק *pasuk* and wants every single phrase to
be meaningful, sometimes the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* just gives common illustrations. So
a common illustration is borrowing wine or oil
or borrowing bread. But in its mind, the wine and oil is
talking about things that men might do, men are in charge of
the wine, who knows? And the bread is the thing that women
might do. That's the way I just think. I don't think that
it means there's any legal significance to this. It's just another example.
Exactly. But you could have asked, why does it have to say
wine and oil? Why not just say
wine? Yes.
But I can't for instance borrow your ox, because wouldn't that be
like a real business transaction if I don't write it down?
No, as opposed to rent?
I mean, like the same thing, why can't I borrow things?
Can I go to your house and borrow some chairs? I have
some company coming over and borrow your folding table?
Yeah, but there's a difference between borrowing an ox, I know we're
going to use it for work.
Oh, yeah, but that's not because of the act of borrowing per
se. That's because of the whole, that's real עובדין דחול uvdin d'chol.
*Uvda d'chol*.
That's real sort of, I'm not going to use it on שבת
shabbos *Shabbos*.
Yeah, yeah. Okay, now let's take a look at the גמרא gemara
*Gemara*. אמר Amar, ליה רבה בר רב חנן לאביי *Amaleh Rava bar
Rav Chanan l'Abaye*. מאי שנא השאילני hashileni, ומאי שנא הלויני *mai shna
hashileini u'mai shna halveini*? Why is it different? Now we discussed what
the different meaning of the words mean, but he's saying what difference
does it make how you frame it, why does it make it
better הלכתית *halachically*? אמר ליה *Amaleh*, he said to him, השאילני hashileni,
לא אתי למכתב ati le-michtav, *hashileini lo ati l'michtav*. With the language
השאילני *hashileini*, it doesn't lead to writing down. הלויני אתי למכתב *halveini
ati l'michtav*. הלויני *halveini* leads to writing down. So here very much
framing it as about a concern of writing again. In the משנה
Mishnah. *Mishnah* you'd not have to say that, again. The גמרא gemara
*Gemara* very much like we sort of just got through discussing, or
we were discussing before the שיעור *shiur* about the issue of רפואה
*refuah*, the בבלי Bavli *Bavli* very often tries to frame these things
as a concern that it will lead to a דאורייתא d'oraita *d'Oraisa*
violation rather than something that is intrinsically problematic, at least at the
rabbinic level. So for the בבלי *Bavli*, a lot of the concerns
around business activities on שבת shabbos *Shabbos* is it'll lead to writing
down. Now you didn't have to say that. You could say business
activities is intrinsically contradictory to the spirit of שבת shabbos *Shabbos*. Okay,
but that's how it understands it. So if it was about the
intrinsic problem of business, you understand if the language that you use
like "can I borrow two eggs" is a language that's more about
not business-like. If it's a language about loans, it's a business-like language.
And that could have been the difference itself, whether it suggests the
world of commerce and business. But the בבלי *Bavli* is very much
framing it as a concern of writing down. So it's saying maybe
that those are linked. When you're suggesting more that world of commerce
and business, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says long term, תוספות tosfos *Tosafot* says
something that gets used up and something else has to be given,
that leads more to writing where something that is more domestic and
short term and giving the thing back doesn't lead to writing. So
it frames it as a writing concern, not as an intrinsic concern.
But it's context dependent. Like if I say "can you loan me
two eggs", we all know it means...
I understand, I said that in English it's hard to... Anyway, the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* says like this. והא *v'ha*... so the גמרא gemara
*Gemara* says okay, so the גמרא gemara *Gemara* isn't so happy. So
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says one minute, והא כיון דבכל זימנא דבעי
למימר הלויני ואמר ליה השאילני *v'ha keivan d'bechol zimna d'ba'i l'meimar halveini
v'amaleh hashileini*. I don't get it, says the גמרא gemara *Gemara*. Sometimes
maybe like Michael was saying, the right term, the technical term to
use would be הלויני *halveini*, but you say השאילני *hashileini*. People aren't
precise exactly which term to use. ולא קפדי עליה *v'lo kapdi ilei*.
And people aren't מקפיד makpid, *machpid* to say specifically הלויני *halveini* versus
השאילני *hashileini*. ואתי למכתב *v'ati l'michtav*. And they'll write things down which
are real let's say loans of money and they'll use but they'll
use the term השאילני *hashileini*. שבת shabbos נמי אתי למכתב *Shabbos nami
ati l'michtav*. So even when you say השאילני *hashileini* on שבת Shabbos,
*Shabbos*,
it'll lead to writing it down because that's the term that sometimes
is used in the other context as well. אמר ליה *Amaleh*. אמר
ליה, so we'll skip the parenthesis, he said to him, בשבת כיון
דהשאילני הוא דשרי ליה רבנן הלוויני לא שרי ליה. beshabas keivan dehashileni
hu desharei lei rabanan halveni lo sharei lei. No,
yes it's true sometimes people are not a hundred percent precise. But
since the rabbi said the only term you can use on שבת
Shabbos. is השאילני, you can't use the term הלוויני, halveni, so מנכרא
מילתא ולא אתי למכתב. minkara milsa velo asi lemichtav.
Almost it's like it's a signal to myself like if I remember
that I have to use the term השאילני, it's reminding me that,
you know, this is שבת Shabbos. and I have to be careful
about how I'm going about this whole thing. Okay, so by by
so by creating these types of restrictions, you know, a, it gives
you a normal default context for the transaction and b, it really
serves as a reminder. Okay, so that's how the גמרא's Gemara explaining
the difference but again framing it as a concern of coming to
write. אמר ליה רבה בר רב חנא לאביי. amar lei rabba bar
rav chana le'abaye. So רבה בר רב חנא rabba bar rav chana
said to אביי, abaye, מכדי, michdi, let's take a look. אמרו רבנן
כל מילי דיומא טובא כמה דאפשר לשנויי משנינן. amru rabanan kol milei
deyoma tova kama de'efshar leshunaye meshaninan. The rabbis said anything relating to
יום טוב, yom tov, you should do with a שינוי shinuy as
much as possible. Now what does that mean? It means even things
that are permissible if they are the types of activities that are
more like עובדא דחול, uvda dechol, again, because that's like the context
here like weekday-like activities which is exactly our blueprint where what makes
it weekday. But things that maybe are very laborious, you know, and
very much involving yourselves in sort of like mundane needs, so these
weekday activities we try to do it with a שינוי. shinuy. We
try to do עובדא דחול uvda dechol in a slightly different way.
Okay, so הני נשי, hani nashi, there you go again now mentioning
women for no other purpose other than that this is what was
the common case, דמלין חצבייהו מיא, demalyan chatzvayehu maya, they fill their
buckets with water. מאי טעמא לא משניין? mai ta'ama lo mshanyan? Why
do we let them fill their buckets with water on יום טוב
yom tov the same way they do during the weekday? Why don't
we try to do it with a שינוי? shinuy? Because you know
going out to the well and drawing water is a very laborious
activity. You would still have to do it on יום טוב, yom
tov, what choice would you have? You didn't have running water. But
it feels very עובדא דחול, uvda dechol, it feels very weekday. So
why don't we do it with a שינוי? shinuy?
So what do you do differently?
So that's what he's going to say. So it says משום דלא
אפשר mishum delo efshar because there's really no alternative. היכי לעבדי? heichi
le'avdi? What do you want to do differently? דמליא בחצבא רבה למלי
בחצבא זוטא, demalya bechatzva rabba lemly bechatzva zuta, those that use big
buckets should use small buckets, הא קא מפשא בהלוכא, ha ka mafsha
behilucha, then they'll just have to make more trips, so that'll be
more טירחא. tircha. So that's not going to make anything any
better. דמליא בחצבא זוטא למלי בחצבא רבה, demalya bechatzva zuta lemly bechatzva
rabba, those that use small buckets they should now start using big
buckets, הא קא מפשא במשאוי, ha ka mafsha bemasavye, then they'll have
to it'll have to be heavier. So, you know, you don't win.
It makes things, you know, also, you know, contradicts other שבת Shabbos.
values, you know, to make a שינוי, shinuy, you know, either you'll
make it, you know, make it take longer or you'll make it
more difficult. So those aren't options. ניפריס סודרא, nifris sudara, so maybe
you should like do something different with the bucket, like put a
put a put some type of a cloth, you know, over part
of the bucket, so at least it's some type of a physical
היכר heker that things are different. אזיל לידי סחיטה, azil lidei schita,
the cloth will get wet and you'll come to squeeze.
Put a bow on it.
נכסייה בנחתמא, nechasye benachtama,
cover it with some type of like Michael says of some type
of cover that's not a cloth. Okay so then no. זימנין דמיפסיק,
zimnin demifsik, if you demand that there needs to be some type
of a partial cover on the bucket, sometimes the string that's holding
that bucket down will break ואתי למקטריה ve'asi lemiktarei and they'll have
and they'll come to knot it. Even so. Okay yeah I guess
so like before we had the silver the silver scrapers. Anyway so
the גמרא Gemara. says הלכך לא אפשר. hilkach lo efshar. Therefore there's
not real option. Okay now I do want to say that this
תוספות tosfos was not really on our גמרא Gemara was quoting a
parallel סוגיא sugya in ביצה beitzah
was only on our גמרא Gemara to the degree that some people
had that written in our גמרא Gemara but תוספות tosfos says it's
crossed it out doesn't belong. But the question becomes let's say you
do have these competing values. On the one hand עובדא דחול uvda
dechol and on the other hand טירחא. tircha. Now טירחא tircha is
not exactly the same as עובדא דחול. uvda dechol. טירחא tircha specifically
relates to exertion and effort like, you know, whereas עובדא דחול uvda
dechol somehow again pulls you out of the שבת Shabbos, day and
brings you more into, you know, the weekday. It's hard to exactly
define what's that context. So תוספות tosfos says anyway when those two
are competing we are more willing to say do more טירחא tircha
so that it does not feel like a weekday. Okay that the
bigger value the more important value is the is the עובדא דחול
uvda dechol than the טירחא. tircha. So he says but so this
גמרא Gemara so why not then in this גמרא Gemara make more
trips or bigger trips
let the עובדא דחול uvda dechol concern outweigh טירחא? tircha? תוספות Tosafot
says no because here no matter how you did it it's all
it's still going to remain עובדא דחול. uvda dechol. Right? Going to
the water and drawing the water however many trips you make however
big your bucket is is a very is a feels like a
very weekday activity. So the only value you get is a value
of שינוי, shinuy, you know, of doing something just for the sake
of making it different but it doesn't experientially make it less of
a weekday activity and therefore the גמרא Gemara says that does not
justify, you know, increasing the trips or increasing the burden. But if
you could really make it less of a weekday activity by making
and and it means
the more effort would win out. So, I mean, I mean the
more weekday activity, the minimizing the weekday activity would win out, even
at the expense of more effort. Let me give you an example
of this. There's an interesting debate of פוסקים Poskim about whether you
can use labor-saving mechanical devices in the kitchen. For example, can you
use let's say a grater? Now normally there's a concern of טוחן,
Tochen, right? You can't like you know grate. But sometimes טוחן Tochen
doesn't apply. Let's say you've got something for example like an egg.
It's not, does not, doesn't grow from the ground. Can you use
like an egg grater, you know? Or cheese, can you use a
cheese grater? So sometimes you might be able to use a peeler
although it might be it's concerns about בורר, Borer, but there are
cases where maybe it's not בורר Borer where you know the thing
is edible and you would normally eat the shell, but or peeling
right making like like what it the stripes, the stripes of the
cucumber and so on. So the שמירת שבת כהלכתה Shmirat Shabbat Kehilchata
says all of that is אסור assur because of עובדא דחול. Uvda
D'chol. רב משה Rav Moshe says it's based on a on a
line in שלחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, but that's the way he interprets
it. רב משה Rav Moshe says since when is it עובדא דחול
Uvda D'chol to use labor-saving devices, right? So he says it's not
assuming it's not other problems of בורר Borer or טוחן, Tochen, רב
משה Rav Moshe says it's fine. But you know where the שמירת
שבת Shmirat Shabbat is coming from it's probably the sense that yes
I understand by saying it's עובדא דחול Uvda D'chol you're going to
have to exert more effort, but it makes things a little more
you know you know a little more removed from the you know
somehow these labor-saving devices are more the I guess the word I'm
looking for is primitive, you know? But it take it it brings
it into a more simple type of an experience out of and
that he feels is part of so exactly what creates עובדא דחול
Uvda D'chol is not clear but it is interesting that while our
גמרא Gemara, our גמרא'ס Gemara's really talking about competing values and concerns
of עובדא דחול Uvda D'chol versus טרחא Tircha and sometimes you can
have more טרחא Tircha and less עובדא דחול. Uvda D'chol. So anyway
that's just the point that תוספות Tosafot makes which is worth mentioning.
Let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara, אמר ליה רבה
בר בר חנה לאביי. Amar lei Rava bar bar Chana l'Abaye. So
רבה בר בר חנה Rava bar bar Chana said to אביי, Abaye,
get this not exactly our case but it's the same רבה בר
בר חנה Rava bar bar Chana to אביי: Abaye: תנן, Tnan, we
taught in the משנה: Mishnah לא מספקין ולא מטפחין ולא מרקדין ביום
טוב. Lo mesapkin v'lo metapchin v'lo merakdin b'Yom Tov. You cannot you
know clap and like you know and מטפחין metapchin like bang like
you know or like you know bang like this, and you can't
dance on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So רש"י Rashi thinks that the
that the that the reason you would sort of clap and and
you know and bang would be out of mourning, but תוספות Tosafos
says no no no we're talking that's a separate problem on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, we're talking even if you're doing it just out
of joy in music, you know, you can't bang and clap and
dance. Why? I understand. So why? So the concern is at least
the way the גמרא Gemara in ביצה Beitzah says the concern is
is that if you're if you're doing it you will come to
go ahead and you know make some you know bring out musical
instruments, fix musical instruments, make musical instruments and so on. Okay so
I want to get back to that in a minute but that's
the הלכה. halacha. Now he says: וכחזינן דעבדין ולא אמרינן להו ולא
מידי. V'kachazeinan d'avdin v'lo amrinan lehu v'lo midi. But people are doing
this and we don't say anything, right? Good thing you know he
didn't come to the HJR, you know like standards! Okay so people
do it, they clap, they dance, we don't say anything, how do
we explain that? So the גמרא Gemara says: ולטעמיך, V'letaimeich, according to
your reasoning, הא דאמר רבא hada d'amar Rava לא ליתי אינש אפומא
דמבואה דלחי lo lisei inash apuma d'mavoya d'leichei what we said a
few days ago that רבא Rava says a person shouldn't sit by
the by the door you know the opening of the of the
alley which has the לחי, lechi, the post that's a היכר heker
not to carry in and out: דילמא מיגנדר ליה חפץ ואתי לאתויי,
Dilma migndar lei cheifetz v'ati l'asvayei, maybe an object will roll out
and you'll come to run after it and pick it up because
you're forgetting the boundary because you're sitting right at against the marker
so you forget that you'll be carrying from רשות הרבים reshut harabim
to רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. והא חזינן דמייתו חצבי ויתבי אפומא דמבואה
ולא אמרינן להו ולא מידי. V'hachazeinan d'masi chatzvi v'yasvi apuma d'mavoya v'lo
amrinan lehu v'lo midi. But we see that the people that draw
you know that draw the water they sit on the by this
opening and and we don't say anything to them. So how do
you so it's another case where we don't bother doing anything, how
do you explain it? So he says: אלא, Ela, הנח לישראל, hanach
l'Yisrael, forget leave the Jewish people alone. מוטב שיהיו שוגגין ואל יהיו
מזידין. Mutav sheyihyu shogegin v'al yihyu mezidin. Better that they should sin
in error rather than willful sin. If they're not going to listen
to us anyway, better to just keep our mouths shut. So right,
so pretty amazing. So now the גמרא Gemara says okay, so so
so סבר מינה הני מילי בדרבנן. savar mina hani mili d'rabanan. He
thought okay maybe that's if they're doing something that's rabbinically problematic, we
don't say anything to them because you know it's rabbinic and they're
שוגג, shogeg, better to be שוגג shogeg than מזיד. mezid. אבל בדאורייתא
לא, Aval b'doraita lo, if it's biblical maybe we have to say
something regardless, A: maybe just to voice protest even if they're not
going to listen, and B: maybe we have to work harder to
get them to listen and we shouldn't just concede the realities because
it's a דאורייתא De-Oraisa, violation. And the גמרא Gemara says very shockingly:
ולא היא, V'lo hi, it's not true, לא שנא בדרבנן ולא שנא
בדאורייתא. lo shna b'drabanan v'lo shna b'doraita. It doesn't matter biblical or
rabbinic, we would keep our mouths shut if it's not going to
do any good. דהא תוספתא... D'ha tosefta... תוספת יום כיפור דאורייתא, Tosefes
Yom Kippur De-Oraisa, adding to יום כיפור Yom Kippur is a Biblical
obligation to start יום כיפור Yom Kippur early. היא. Hi. וכחזינן להו
דקאכלי ושתי, Vechachazinan lehu dekachli veshasi, we see people that eat and
drink עד דתחשך ad detheshach until it literally gets dark, so they
don't add. It sounds also like even during בין השמשות bein hashemashos
maybe. Okay, ולא מיחו להו מידי, vlo mihu lehu midi, we don't
say anything. So the point is, keep your mouth shut if it's
not going to do any good. Now, I do have to tell
you that first of all, the ראשונים Rishonim come and they qualify
this. They say maybe that's דאורייתא'ס De-Oraisas that are not so explicit,
you know, מפורש. mefurash. But if somebody is like, you know, stealing,
you know, and you say, you know, don't say anything, you know,
or, you know, you know, oh, better they should be שוגג. shogeg.
No, at a certain point you have to speak up. And again,
why to speak up if they're not going to listen? Is A,
maybe you have to hope that they will listen even though it's
unlikely, but the bigger the violation and the more blatant it is,
you know, especially if it's if it's an explicit דאורייתא, De-Oraisa. their
ability to claim ignorance, you know, and real שוגג shogeg becomes less.
So therefore, there's more of a demand to speak up number one
with a, you know, they're less שוגג shogeg to begin with. B,
there's a greater, you know, concern, you know, you have to work
harder to hope maybe they'll listen and C, you know, there's an
issue of just voicing protest even if nobody is going to listen
so you shouldn't think that, you know, you shouldn't think and others
shouldn't think that you're okay with it. And it does raise interesting
questions on the one hand about the מצוות תוכחה mitzvah tochecha and
on the other hand about the question about its effectiveness or ineffectiveness
and how to strike that balance. But this is a quite interesting
principle of sometimes, you know, you know, discretion is the better part
of valor, sometimes just keep your piece. It's actually interesting, there's one
תשובה teshuva where he where he I forget who it is, but
the פוסק posek it's a ראשון Rishon was discussing something and then
he sort of ends it by saying אלא הניח להם לישראל
וכו'.
ela
hanach
lahem
l'Yisrael
v'chulu.
And then there's a debate in the later פוסקים, Poskim, did he
mean to say הניח להם לישראל מוטב יהיו שוגגין hanach lahem l'Yisrael
mutav yiheyu shogegin and that therefore what they're doing is wrong, or
there's another הניח להם לישראל. hanach lahem l'Yisrael. Does anybody know the
other הניח להם לישראל? hanach lahem l'Yisrael? הניח להם לישראל אם לא
נביאים הם בני נביאים הם, Hanach lahem l'Yisrael im lav nevi'im heim
bnei nevi'im heim,
which means that, you know, we can assume they're doing the right
thing. So if you say הניח להם לישראל וכו', hanach lahem l'Yisrael
v'chulu, you don't know how to end the sentence. I did want
to say another thing by the way about the clapping and so
on. Again, this gets to the point we were saying that the
בבלי is always framing things as leading to a concern of violating
a דאורייתא. In the תוספתא, Tosefta, this idea of not clapping and
etc. seems that it is much more again an intrinsic problem of
עובדין דחול. uvdin d'chol Why?
Because it would be the type of things farmers would do out
in their fields to scare away the crows. And it was specifically
about like, you know, like getting the birds to fly away. So
it really seems like it was more of that עובדין דחול uvdin
d'chol intrinsic issue, but again the גמרא Gemara reframes it. And because
the גמרא Gemara reframes it, תוספות Tosafos deals with the exact same
problem in this גמרא, Gemara that in תוספות'ס Tosafos's day it was
extremely common for people to ignore this, as it is nowadays. A
lot of people, some people are very מקפיד, makpid you know, when
they clap they do it with the back of their hands, they
don't do, but a lot of people are not מקפיד makpid. on
this. And תוספות Tosafos acknowledges it and תוספות Tosafos says oh it's
because rather than saying like the גמרא, Gemara yes they're sinning but
leave them alone, תוספות actually went even further to rationalize or to
explain it and says nowadays that we don't, you know, so trivially
make or fix musical instruments, so this maybe this whole גזירה gezeirah
would not apply. So once again because it's framed as a concern,
not here where in ביצה Beitzah other places where it's quoted, because
it's framed as not an intrinsic problem but a problem of where
it might lead, that leads to interesting issues about maybe some certain
situations would be different. Okay, but it is also fits into the
whole עובדין דחול discussion that we have been having. Okay, so anyway,
that's the issue. And by the way the other thing to note
is the connection, we start, you know, this issues of רבה בר
רב הונא Rabbah bar Rav Huna to אביי Abaye is about filling
up the חצבא, hatzba, filling up with these buckets. And here the
concern about the about putting things by the by the opening of
the מבוי mavoi is he says דקא חזינא נמי דמותבי חצבי ויתבי
אפימא דמבוא, dechachazinan nami demosevi hatzvi veyasvi apuma demavoa, they take these
buckets of water presumably and they leave them, they stack them up
by the opening of the מבוי mavoi and therefore same as sitting
by the opening of the מבוי, mavoi, it covers over the the
beam and therefore it should be a problem. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues, תשא אישה מחברתה ככרות, Tisha isha mechaveirta kikaros,
a woman can borrow loaves of bread as long as she uses
the right language. So the גמרא Gemara, says בשבת הוא דאסור, B'shabbos
hu de'asur, so here you're saying it's only problematic on שבת, Shabbat
אבל בחול שפיר דמי, aval bechol shapir dami, it suggests during the
week that it's okay. לימא מתניתין דלא כהלל, Leima masnisin d'lo k'Hillel,
this sounds not like הלל, Hillel, דתנן וכן היה הלל אומר, d'tenan
v'chein hayah Hillel omeir, הלל Hillel used to say, לא תלווה אישה
ככר לחברתה, lo talveh isha kikar lachaveirta,
again women borrowing bread, a woman should not lend bread to her
friend עד שתעשנה דמים, ad sheta'asena damim, that what you have to
do is you have to say, okay, look, this bread costs a
buck twenty-five, you owe me dollar twenty-five, not you owe me a
loaf of bread. Why? Because this is a concern called, you know,
פירות בפירות, peiros b'peiros, about borrowing things that are not not based
on their dollar value. but just on the object. What's the concern?
שמא יוקרו חיטים ונמצא בא לידי ריבית, shema yokru chitim venimtza ba
lidei ribis,
maybe the price of flour will go up and when you return
a loaf of bread, it actually will be a more expensive item.
Okay? So therefore you should not buy things and exchange for kind
because it's a concern of ריבית, ribis, you might return something that
is of greater value. So how come here it seems like that
you're allowed to do it? Because you know, if you use the
right language, השילני, hashilini, or if you do it during the weekday
it's allowed. What about Hillel's concern? So the גמרא Gemara. says: אפילו
תימא הלל, afilu teima Hillel, even according to
Hillel, הא באתרא דקייץ דמיה הא באתרא דלא קייץ דמיה. ha be-atra
de-kayitz damei ha be-atra de-lo kayitz damei. If the value is clear
and is set like everybody knows that there's a fixed value, you
know, for bread, so then,
then it's not going to lead to ריבית. ribis. Why won't it
lead to ריבית? ribis? Maybe that fixed value will go up? So
רש"י Rashi says: yeah, the fixed value will go up but everybody
will know it went up so you'll make sure to like, you
know, adjust accordingly.
What does that mean?
Meaning if you give three-quarters
of a loaf of bread?
You'll give three-quarters of a loaf of bread. Right. Which is pretty
funny because you could really think, you know, or רש"י Rashi, says
you'll pay or רש"י, Rashi you know, רש"י says you'll pay
what the value was when you borrowed it. Since it was clear
that a loaf of bread goes for a dollar, you know, I'll
know if if now the price has changed, I'll just know to
give you back a dollar. But if the value was indeterminate, you
know, so I wouldn't know how much money to give you back
either. Right? So therefore, so if so basically what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is you do have to be concerned about this as
a general rule according to Hillel. Right? But the point is is
that how are you concerned about it? So if the amount is
indeterminate, so then you have to set the amount when you borrow
it. If the amount is well-defined at that moment, everybody knows how
much a loaf of bread is, then there's no need to set
the amount. The amount's already clear. But that doesn't mean you can
return a loaf of bread. That still means that you're supposed to
give back the value of it, you know, and so on. So
this is a real issue because when you borrow things from your
next-door neighbor, like people don't do that at all. Right? So so,
you know, how much do we actually do this in practice? You
know, I try to actually say 'can I have', not 'can I
borrow', or you know, which is again funny because it's still... what?
No, the egg was fifty cents and now seventy-five cents, you're giving
them back two eggs?
No, I say can I have, I don't give it back.
Oh,
you
don't give it back? You know,
or you know, or I'll give it back afterwards, but I'll give
it back as a מתנה. matanah. But there's a real problem that
people, you know, are not now are you know are not so
מקפיד. Now part of the reason could be that a lot of
products nowadays, even if you give back a little more, an egg
that's a little bigger or a little smaller, but you know, there
is like pretty much like a standard price of these things that
doesn't fluctuate that much. But nevertheless, it you know it is an
issue and they will discuss it more when we get to בבא
מציעא Bava Metzia and discuss ריבית. ribis. Yes.
In Israel the price of much bread is regulated by the government.
Right. And from time to time they do change it. Right. So
day to day usually not.
Right, right. So anyway, but the דקייץ דמיה de-kayitz damei here means
just means that you still have to be sensitive to it, it's
just you know what the amount is. Okay, so that's an interesting
discussion that we can have more of when we get to בבא
מציעא. Bava Metzia. Let's take a look. איתמר. Itmar. אם אינו מאמינה,
im eino ma'amina, if you don't believe him you leave your jacket.
איתמר. Itmar. הוות יום טוב. Havas Yom Tov. Now, let's say you
did one of these things, you borrowed on יום טוב Yom Tov
or on שבת. Shabbat And now you have to, and now it's
after שבת. Shabbat So I quote unquote borrowed some eggs or borrowed
a sheep. Okay? So רב יוסף אמר לא ניתנה ליתבע. Rav Yosef
amar lo nitna l'itava. And then afterwards I say, yeah, you know,
we never said that I actually had to pay you back, right?
You just sort of quote unquote gave it to me, so I'm
actually not going to pay it back to you. Okay? Can you
now bring me, obviously I'm doing something unethical and so on, but
can you now actually sue me in court? Can you actually now
bring me to דין? din? רב יוסף Rav Yosef says לא ניתנה
ליתבע, lo nitna l'itava, you can't bring the guy to דין. din.
It's all on a trust system. Okay? ורב אמר ניתנה ליתבע. ve-Rav
amar nitna l'itava. No, you can bring him to דין, din, it's
not a trust, he really does owe you that money or that
object. רב יוסף אמר לא ניתנה ליתבע, Rav Yosef amar lo nitna
l'itava, you cannot bring him to court. דאי אמרת ניתנה ליתבע, de-im
amart nitna l'itava, if you say you can bring him to court,
אתי למכתב, so then you're going to, you know, again, then it's
a... if you've turned it into a real debt, so I'll write
it down to remember it. If it remains as a trust system,
so I know going in it's a trust system, I'm not going
to write it down. But if I know I'm entitled to it,
I'm going to make a record to make sure that I'm going
to get it back. רבא אמר ניתנה ליתבע. Rava amar nitna l'itava.
No, you can bring him to דין. din. דאי אמרת לא ניתנה,
de-im amarta lo nitna, because if you say that you cannot bring
him to דין, din, לא יהיב ליה, lo ya'iv leh, so then
he won't give. Who's going to have that degree of trust? ואתי
לאמנועי משמחת יום טוב, ve-ati limnumey mi-simchas Yom Tov, and then people
won't be able to have the שמחת יום טוב simchas Yom Tov
of borrowing these types of things. It's interesting that it frames it
as יום טוב, Yom Tov, not as שבת. Shabbat Our משנה Mishnah,
is on שבת, Shabbat but maybe it's even a bigger issue on
יום טוב Yom Tov because there's more things you can borrow because
you could be actually making food. And you know, if you're actually
making food, there's more things... oh my god, I'm out of eggs!
That's more common and there's more of a שמחת יום טוב simchas
Yom Tov type of an issue. You might not have your basic
meals for יום טוב Yom Tov prepared yet and you really need
to borrow. Anyway, me too.
I back, you know, if I don't trust you... I'm not going
to have שמחת יום טוב. Simchas Yom Tov.
Right. Right, well, right, right. Yes. So there are these competing concerns.
Look, the other thing you could also say is, is that if
it's ניתנה ליתבע, Nitnah Litvah, you've turned it into a more business
transaction, you know, but again the Gemara makes it less about the
business transaction per se and about the concern about writing it down.
So let's take a look. תנן, Tnan, we taught our Mishna. אינו
מאמינו מניח טליתו אצלו. Eino maamino maniach taliso etzlo. If he doesn't
believe him, he leaves his, you know, if he doesn't believe him,
the other guy leaves his garment with him. אי אמרת בשלמא לא
ניתנה ליתבע, Ei amart bishlama lo nitnah litvah, if you cannot bring
it to din, now we understand why you want to hold on
to the tallis, ועושים חשבון אחר השבת, V’osim cheshbon achar ha-shabbos, and
therefore I've got your tallis, you're going to have to pay up
if you want your tallis back. אלא אי אמרת ניתנה ליתבע, Ela
ei amart nitnah litvah, but if I could bring him
to din, so אמאי מניח טליתו אצלו? Amai maniach taliso etzlo? Why
do you have to, why would I have to hold on to
the tallis? ליתן ליה, Liyiten leh, I'll give you your eggs or
your whatever you need, your wine, and if you don't pay me,
ולתבעיה, Ul’itvaye, and I'll bring you to din. Now of course part
of the problem would be, I don't exactly have any evidence. Right.
So anyway, that's not what the Gemara says. The Gemara says אמר,
no, because he could say, לא בעינא דאיקום בדינא ודיינא. Lo beina
d’eikum bedina v’dayana. I don't want to go to a Beis Din
and deal with judges and the whole thing. So even if technically
I could, I still want your tallis. I still want to make
a shortcut not to have to bother with all that, so that
doesn't prove that I don't have the ability to do it if
I needed to. Okay. So מתיב רבידי בר אבין. Masiv Ravidi bar
Avin. So Ravidi bar Avin asks. השוחט את הפרה וחילקה, Hashochet es
haparah vechilkah, somebody who shechted a parah and divided it up, you
know, gave out the meat, בראש השנה. Be-Rosh Hashana. This is on
Rosh Hashana. So people didn't have enough meat, there was a butcher,
he shechted the cow, he gave it to various customers. אם היה
חודש מעובר. Im hayah chodesh me'ubar. Now this is the end of
the Shmita year, the Rosh Chodesh going into year eight. What happens
at the end of a Shmita year?
Debt gets canceled.
Debts get canceled. So if I am giving you this meat on
credit and I'm giving it to you a minute before Rosh Hashana
is over, before the seventh year is over, Rosh Hashana of the
eighth comes, Rosh Hashana of the eighth, your debt is canceled. So
I gave it to you on the first day of Rosh Hashana.
Here's the question: Is the first day of Rosh Hashana on day
eight the first day of Tishrei or the 30th day of, right,
of Elul? Okay, today it's... I understand what it is these days.
So אם היה חודש מעובר, Im hayah chodesh me'ubar, if it was
a full month, so the first day of Rosh Hashana was the
30th day of Elul, משמט, Meshamet, then all of your loans get
canceled. So all you guys who got from the butcher, you really
lucked out. ואם לאו, Ve-im lav, but if—I mean you still owe
it to
them, don't you?
Well, that's a... well, that's a separate question but we won't worry
about that right now. And we'll talk about that in a minute.
ואם לאו, Ve-im lav, but if not, if it was the first
day of Tishrei, אינו משמט. Eino meshamet. Okay. So now the Gemara
says, ואי לא ניתנה ליתבע. Ve-ei lo nitnah litvah. Now remember, he
was doing it on the first day of Rosh Hashana, which is
Yom Tov. So when he was giving it, it was exactly this
type of a thing of giving something in a without a explicit
use of the word buy, loan, right? It was exactly this type
of a thing being done on Yom Tov. So if you couldn't
bring the guy to court regardless, מאי משמט? Mai meshamet? Why do
you have to say that it... the loans are annulled? The loans
are annulled is the point about the ability to collect in court.
Since this stuff was given on Yom Tov anyway, there would have
been a, you know, there would have been no ability to collect
in court. So it sounds like it was a real loan, there
was a real ability to collect in court, and Shmita annulled it.
So the Gemara says, no. Here's why. Here's why you could have
collected in court. שאני התם דאגלאי מילתא דחול הוא. Shani hasam de'iglai
milsa de-chol hu. The whole point is that it turns out that
the first day of Rosh Hashana was the 30th day of Elul.
Right? What's the scenario where it gets annulled? When the first day
of Rosh Hashana turned out to be the 30th day of Elul.
So then it wasn't a Yom Tov loan, it was a weekday
loan, and therefore, right, you understand why when it turned out to
be... so that's why it would have been a real loan and
you needed Shmita to be meshamet. Okay. So now the Gemara says
like this: תא
שמע Ta shema מסיפא, M'seifa, the end. ואם לאו, Ve-im lav, if
it was not a
30-day Elul, it was genuinely the first day of Tishrei, אינו משמט,
Eino meshamet, it does not annul it. אי אמרת בשלמא ניתנה ליתבע,
Ei amart bishlama nitnah litvah, if you say that the loan normally
could be collected, so היינו דקתני אינו משמט. Hainu deka tani eino
meshamet. So now we have, I gave you this meat on the
first day of Tishrei, Shmita did not annul it, and therefore the
suggestion is Shmita did not annul it and therefore what? I can
get my money. Right? So we understand by saying eino meshamet means
I can get my money. היינו דקתני אינו משמט. Hainu deka tani
eino meshamet. אלא אי אמרת לא ניתנה ליתבע, Ela ei amart lo
nitnah litvah, if even forgetting Shmita I can't get my money because
it was the first day of Tishrei and it was a Yom
Tov loan, so אמאי אינו משמet? Amai eino meshamet? What do you
mean to say Shmita doesn't annul? Who cares? Right? You understand the
scenario? It winds up the butcher gave it to me on the
first day of Tishrei and it says sorry guys, Shmita didn't annul
it. Big deal. They're not... they can't be forced to come to
a Beis Din anyway. So what's the point of discussing whether Shmita
annulled it? So the Gemara says, דיהבי ליה ושקיל. Dihavi leh v’shakil.
Here's the... If שמיטה Shemittah annulled it, if I'm a good guy,
you can't bring me to court, but hopefully I'm a good guy
and I'm going to come with my money and I'm, so can
you accept the money that I come with after יום טוב? Yom
Tov? If שמיטה Shemittah annulled it, you shouldn't even accept the money.
Right, but we'll talk about that. But if שמיטה Shemittah didn't annul
it, then I'm a good guy and I come with my money,
you take my money. One minute, the גמרא Gemara says, מכלל דרישא
יהבי ליה ולא שקיל. mikh-lal de-reisha yahvi leh velo shakil.
You mean to tell me when שמיטה Shemittah annuls it like in
the first case, you can't take the money even if I offer
it? So we're going to see in a minute you can. גמרא
Gemara says no, רישא צריך למימר ליה משמט אני. reisha tzarikh lemeimar
leh meshamet ani.
If שמיטה Shemittah annuls a debt and the guy comes with his
money, you as the lender have to first say, you know what,
I annul it. And then only if he insists and says, no,
no, no, take it anyway, are you allowed to take the money
that somebody's coming to pay up. סיפא, Seifa, in the case where
there's no annulment of שמיטה, Shemittah, לא צריך למימר ליה משמט אני.
lo tzarikh lemeimar leh meshamet ani.
You can just accept the money straight. Obviously he's paying money for
the meat you gave him. To the, now let me talk about
in a משנה, Mishnah, המחזיר חוב בשביעית. ha-machzir chov be-shevi'it.
Somebody returns a debt on שמיטה. Shemittah. Yes, שמיטה Shemittah annulled it,
but I am coming to pay you up regardless. יאמר לו, yomar
lo, you the lender have to say to me,
משמט אני. meshamet ani. I'm, no, I'm sorry, I annul it, don't
give me your money, it's annulled. ואם אמר לו אף על פי
כן, ve-im amar lo af al pi chen, but if I say
to you, I understand you're annulling it, I still want you to
take the money back, then יקבל ממנו, ykabel mimenu, then you can
accept it, משום שנאמר וזה דבר השמיטה. mishum she-ne'emar ve-zeh devar ha-shemittah.
This is the matter, the word of שמיטה, Shemittah, which makes an
obligation on the lender to say the words of שמיטה, Shemittah, the
words of annulment. So even if the money is offered, he have
to verbally annul. So here's what we're saying. It was a יום
טוב Yom Tov loan. It's true that you're never going to be
able to bring this guy to בית דין, Beit Din, but everybody,
what the implicit trust here is, expectation is, that he'll come afterwards
and pay you for it, which is fine, you can take it.
If, however, it had been affected by שמיטה, Shemittah, then you couldn't
just take the money. Then you would have to say, I annul
it, and you could only take the money if he insisted and
said, nevertheless and regardless. Okay? So both cases the person can't be
forced in דין, Din, but in one case you take the money
as soon as he offers and in the שמיטה Shemittah case you
have to push him off and you have to try to annul
it. רב אביא, Rav Avya, just to end this, רב אביא שקיל
משכונא. Rav Avya shakil mashkona. רב אביא Rav Avya when he gave
people food on יום טוב Yom Tov or whatever, would take a
collateral. And here, by the way, Michael, like you asked in the
משנה, Mishnah it actually explicitly labels it as משכון, mashkon, as collateral.
So maybe you don't have to use trick language. Maybe again, if
the ישוב yishuv is only about writing and not about business per
se, maybe you can even say, I need you to leave collateral.
That's certainly the way the גמרא Gemara is framing it. רבא בר
עולא... Rabba bar Ulla...
Are you going to write it down? Because then maybe I'm going
to claim it was always mine and
then you're going to lose... I don't know, I don't know. Anyway,
רבא בר עולא מארי דארומי. Rabba bar Ulla marei d'arumi. רבא בר
עולא Rabba bar Ulla did a scheme. What does it mean a
scheme? There was, I lent
you, I'm the butcher let's say, I gave you some meat, okay?
And then comes afterwards and I, after יום טוב Yom Tov and
before I even ask you to pay up, and I go to
your house and I say, can I just borrow your car for
an hour? Okay? And then when, when you want your car back,
I say, well first pay me up for my debt. So he
would manage to get some object of the person's after יום טוב
Yom Tov and then hold onto it till he got paid back.
Okay, let's just, I know it's almost over, but let's just go
to the משנה. וכן ערב פסח. ve-khen Erev Pesach. So ערב פסח
Erev Pesach similar thing, you can get your sheep from the guy
and work it out afterwards. So אמר רב יוחנן, Amar Rav Yochanan,
מקדישין פסחך בשבת וחגיגתך ביום טוב. makdishin pesachcha be-Shabbat ve-chagigatecha be-Yom Tov.
Even though you're normally not allowed to sanctify קרבנות korbanot on שבת
Shabbat or יום טוב, Yom Tov, you can do it לצורך שבת
le-tzorech Shabbat and לצורך יום טוב. le-tzorech Yom Tov. What would be
a לצורך שבת le-tzorech Shabbat to sanctify? שבת Shabbat, is ערב פסח
Erev Pesach and you haven't sanctified your קרבן פסח korban Pesach yet,
you can do it. Or it's יום טוב Yom Tov and you
have to bring a חגיגה, chagiga, a certain קרבן korban you bring
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, and you haven't sanctified it yet. So
even though you don't sanctify on שבת Shabbos, and יום טוב, Yom
Tov, you can do it if you need to do it for
that day. לימא מסייע ליה, lima mesaye leh, let's bring a proof.
It's our משנה. וכן ערב פסח בירושלים שחל להיות בשבת, ve-khen Erev
Pesach bi-Yerushalayim she-chal lihyot be-Shabbat, מניח טליתו אצלו. mani'ach talito etzlo. So
if this happened, you didn't have your sheep yet, you leave your
טלית, tallit, ונוטל את פסחו, ve-notel et pishcho, you get your פסח,
Pesach, ועושה עמו חשבון לאחר יום טוב, ve-oseh imo cheshbon le-achar Yom
Tov,
and you work it out after יום טוב. Yom Tov. So you
see, you got your sheep first on שבת Shabbos? and you're going...
so obviously how are you going to make it a קרבן פסח?
korban Pesach? You're going to sanctify it. So you see, you can
sanctify your sheep on שבת Shabbos. if you have to for your
קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. So the גמרא Gemara says, הכא במאי עסקינן,
hacha be-mai askinan, no, what are we talking about here? בממנה אחרים
עמו על פסחו. bi-mmaneh acherim imo al pishcho. I'm really not giving
you the sheep, I sanctified the קרבן פסח korban Pesach already. You
didn't join up with a group, so on שבת Shabbos. I'm including
you in the group. But to include you in the group, you
got to pay to buy in, right? Because it still was my
money, I bought the sheep. So that's what we're talking about, your
paying to buy in is what we work out after שבת, Shabbos.
but you don't really take a sheep that has not been sanctified.
Again, doesn't sound like that at all from the משנה. The משנה
sounds like you're getting a sheep, here we're saying you're paying... to
include you in the group, but to include you in the group,
you gotta pay to buy in, right? Cause it still was my
money; I bought the sheep. So that's what we're talking about; you're
paying to buy in is what we work out after שבת, Shabbos
but you don't really take a sheep that has not been sanctified.
Again, doesn't sound like that at all from the משנה. The משנה
sounds like you're getting the sheep. Here we're saying you're paying to
buy in to an existing קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So the גמרא
says דמעיקרא מקדש וקאי, Demeikara Mikdash Ve'kai, that it was already sanctified.
So that's how it gets out of it. והנן תנן, Vehanan Tnan,
one minute, we have a משנה, אין נמנין על בהמה בתחילה ביום
טוב, Ein Nimnin Al Behema Betchila Beyom Tov, you can't be partnering
with an animal on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Now that actually is
not talking about a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach at all and some
people even cross this line out of the גמרא, doesn't—it's not really
a relevant case. But anyway, שאני הכא כיון דרגיל אצלו כמאן דאמני
ביה מעיקרא דמי. Shani Hacha Kivan Deragil Etzlo Keman De'imni Bei Me'ikara
Dami. So here it says, well, you know, since you may be
our commonly—I'm the guy you buy from, I already somewhat anticipated that
you would be part of this group. None of that—the question and
answer don't make sense because if I had already made you part
of the פסח, Pesach, what are we doing that's new on שבת?
Shabbos Anyway, so a lot of people cross those two lines out
of the גמרא. Let's go to the next case. והתני רב הושעיה,
Vehatni Rav Hoshaia, but רב הושעיה Rav Hoshaia taught, הולך אדם אצל
רועה הרגיל אצלו ונותן לו טלה לפסחו, Holech Adam Etzel Roeh Haragil
Etzlo Venoten Lo Taleh Lepsacho, I go to a shepherd who, you
know, this guy
knows me, he gives me a sheep, ומקדישו, Umakdisho, and it explicitly
says, I get the sheep and what do I do? I sanctify
it. ויוצא בו, Veyotze Bo, and use it for my קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, and we make up after שבת. Shabbos So you see
you sanctify it on שבת. התם נמי כיון דרגיל אצלו אקדושי ליה
מעיקרא. Hatam Nami Kivan Deragil Etzlo Akdushei Lei Me'ikara. No, there too,
the shepherd was expecting you to come by, so he sanctified it
for you ahead of time. So when you showed up, he gave
you something that was already sanctified. So the גמרא says והא מקדיש
תני, Veha Makdish Tani, but what do you mean? It says you
get the sheep and you sanctify it. So the גמרא says הקדש
עילוי מדרבנן. Hekdesh Ilui Miderabbanan. That's just a second הקדש Hekdesh rabbinically
that you should do the act of being מקדיש, Makdish, but you
didn't really need to, it was really done by the shepherd. A
very, very forced reads. All these cases make it clear you can
get your sheep and sanctify it. The גמרא is trying to turn
them into special cases where that's not what happened. So the גמרא
says anyway, but that's רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's position, and we're trying
to say it's not proven by the משנה, but it pretty much
does seem to be the case. So now the גמרא just ends,
לימא רבי יוחנן הכי, Liemar Rabbi Yochanan Hachi, did רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan really say that? ואמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה. Ve'amar Rabbi
Yochanan Halacha Kistam Mishna. He says we rule like a סתם משנה.
Stam Mishna. ותנן, Utnan, the משנה says, לא מקדישין ולא מעריכין ולא
מחרימין ולא מגביהין תרומות ומעשרות. Lo Makdishin Velo Maarichin Velo Machrimin Velo
Magbihin Terumot Umaserot. You don't sanctify and you don't give other types
of donations to, you know, הקדש Hekdesh and so on, and תרומות
ומעשרות. Terumot Umaserot. כל אלו ביום טוב אמרו קל וחומר בשבת. Kol
Elu Beyom Tov Amru Kal Vachomer Beshabbos. You don't do it on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, certainly on שבת. So now we're finally getting
to the principle. Why can you sanctify stuff, your קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, you're not allowed to sanctify on שבת or יום טוב? Yom
Tov? And the answer is obvious. לא קשיא כאן בחובות שקבוע להן
זמן כאן בחובות שאין קבוע להן זמן. Lo Kashya Kan Bechovot Shekavuah
Lahen Zman Kan Bechovot She'ein Kavuah Lahen Zman.
It's a question whether you have to do it today or not.
You have to bring the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach today, you can
sanctify your קרבן פסח Korban Pesach today. If it's something that you
don't have to do today on שבת and today on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, then you don't sanctify on שבת anymore.